

Kenneth Atz

Curriculum Vitae

I am a PhD student at ETH Zürich and I am strongly interested in the fields of machine learning applied to drug science, chemistry and biomedicine. During my studies I was able to gain valuable insights into a variety of interdisciplinary academic research groups and I was given the opportunity to complete an internship at Roche. I am critically thinking, open-minded, resilient, and strive to challenge the status quo.

Education

2019 - present PhD Student, Machine learning for drug discovery.

Research Group of Prof. Gisbert Schneider, ETH Zürich

2017 - 2019 Master of Science in Chemistry, 5.8/6.

Faculty of Science, University of Basel

2014 - 2017 Bachelor of Science in Chemistry, 5.3/6.

Faculty of Science, University of Basel

Relevant Experience

Sept. 2019 - **Doctoral Candidate**, Research Group of Prof. Gisbert Schneider, ETH Zürich.

present Machine learning for drug discovery

2019 Research Assistant, Supervisor: Prof. Sebastian Hiller, Biozentrum, University of Basel.

Content: Structural biology of pro-inflammatory cytokines and chaperones.

Acquired skills: Multidimensional NMR experiments for backbone assignment of proteins, PCR, western-blots plasmid design *in vivo* migration assays with macrophages. [7 m.]

2018-2019 Master's student, Supervisor: Prof. Anatole von Lilienfeld, University of Basel.

Content: Machine learning reaction yields with Kernel-based methods.

Acquired skills: Python, git, *ab initio* first principle calculations, molecular representation and Kernel-based machine learning methods. [4 m.]

2017 - 2018 Internship, Supervisor: Dr. Uwe Grether, Pharma Research and Early Development (pRED), F. Hoffmann-La Roche Ltd, Basel.

Content: Design, synthesis and evaluation of novel ligands, fluorescent probes and PET tracers optimized for their bioactivity, selectivity and physicochemical properties targeting the endocannaboid system. **Acquired skills:** Drug design and development, extensive scope of organic chemical reactions. [9 m.]

Programming and Software Skills

Programming Languages: Fluency in Python; Intermediate C++, Swift; Java, HTML | **Machine/Deep Learning Frameworks:** PyTorch, Tensorflow | **Databases:** SQL | **QM:** Psi4 **Software:** PyMol, Chem-Draw, Topspin, MOE

Further Experiences and Education

2016 - 2017 Tutor for Organic Chemistry and Mathematics, University of Basel 2015 Civil Service, Felix Platter-Spital, next to a full-time semester [7 m.]

Language Skills

German Native

English Fluent in spoken and written

Hobbies

Photography, surfing, running and German and English literature.

Publications

2019 T. Gazzi *et. al.* Drug Derived Fluorescent Probes for the Specific Visualization of Cannabinoid Type 2 Receptor-A Toolbox Approach ChemRxiv10283027, **2019**, submitted

R. Sarott *et. al.* Highly Specific, Fluorescent Cannabinoid Type 2 Receptor Probes Enable Applications in Microscopy, Flow Cytometry and FRET-based Binding Assays ChemRxiv10288547 **2019**, submitted

A. Haider et. al. Structure—Activity Relationship Studies of Pyridine-Based Ligands and Identification of a Fluorinated Derivative for Positron Emission Tomography Imaging of Cannabinoid Type 2 Receptors J. Med. Chem. **2019**, accepted

K. Weiland *et. al.* Mechanical Stabilization of Helical Chirality in a Macrocyclic Oligothiophene *J. Am. Chem. Soc.* **2019**, 141, 5, 2104

Conference Contributions

2018 International Cannabinoid Research Society (ICRS), Leiden, Netherlands

Awards

2013 Gold Medallist, Swiss Chemistry Olympiad, ETH Zürich